MINSOO KIM

E-mail: mik226@ucsd.edu

San Diego, CA 92093 | +1-858-361-6821 | minsookim.me

Summary

I am a PhD student at UC San Diego in the digital VLSI physical design and the Electronic Design Automation (EDA) area. I currently research at VLSI CAD Laboratory (ABKGroup) under the supervision of Prof. Andrew B. Kahng. Before joining UCSD, I worked in the Design Technology team at Samsung as a physical design engineer and developed physical design methodologies for advanced technology nodes (Samsung Foundry 7, 8, 10, 14 and 28nm technologies). My research interests lie in technology-aware physical design methodology, design-technology cooptimization (DTCO), open-source EDA and machine learning-based prediction/optimization for physical design.

Skills

Research Skills

- SoC physical design flows from RTL to GDS
- Develop an open-sourced academic physical design flow from RTL to GDS (OpenROAD)
- Technology-aware physical design optimization
- Design and Technology Co-Optimization (DTCO)
- Machine learning in physical design

Programming Language Skills

- Verilog HDL, Tcl, C/C++, Python, Perl
- Version control software: Git. Perforce

Electronic Design Automation (EDA) Tools

- Synthesis: Design Compiler, Genus
- Place and Route: IC compiler (ICC), IC compiler II (ICC2) and Innovus
- Static Timing Analysis: Primetime and Tempus
- Design Verification: Calibre and IC Validator
- · Power Integrity Verification: Redhawk and Voltus

Experience

Graduate Student Researcher / VLSI CAD Laboratory University of California, San Diego

09/2017 to Present La Jolla, CA, USA

- Developed DTCO methodology for PPAC evaluations at an early stage of technology development
- Developed Machine Learning (ML)-assisted pathfinding for advanced nodes (w/ Qualcomm)
- Developed Technology-aware leakage optimization and power stapling methodology for advanced nodes (w/ Samsung)
- Developed top-level clock tree synthesis (CTS) optimization for memory-dominant system-on-chip (SoC)
- Participated in an open-sourcing research project (OpenROAD) (https://theopenroadproject.org) supported by DARPA
- Experienced with 7, 12, 14, 16, 28, 45, 65 and 130nm technologies from multiple academia/industry PDKs
- Collaboration with Qualcomm, Samsung, Intel, Arm, NXP and the C-DEN center (http://cden.ucsd.edu)
- Teaching Assistant (TA) for VLSI Integrated Circuits and Systems Design (ECE260B/CSE241A, Lecturer: Prof. Andrew B. Kahng) in Winter 2019

Interim Engineering Intern / Design Technology Team Qualcomm Technologies, Inc.

06/2021 to 09/2021 San Diego, CA, USA (Remote)

• Enable PROBE2.0 (link) for routability assessment and IR drop analysis at 4nm technology

Software Intern / Digital and Signoff Group **Cadence Design Systems**

06/2020 to 09/2020 Austin, TX, USA (Remote)

 Developed a buffering methodology for detailed balancing of clock trees in clock tree synthesis stage (ccopt, Innovus)

Physical Design Engineer / Design Technology Team

02/2013 to 07/2017 Hwaseong-si, South Korea

Samsung Electronics

- Developed physical design methodologies for Samsung 7, 8, 10, 14, 28nm technology nodes
- Developed reference flow scripts and technology files of ICC and ICC2 for Samsung 10, 14, 28nm technology
- Enabled new design rules in P&R tools for 10, 14, 28nm technology nodes
- Technical support for Samsung foundry customers (Qualcomm, NVIDIA, AMD, ST Microelectronics)
- Worked with EDA vendors (Cadence, Synopsys and Mentor Graphics) for tool development at advanced technologies
- Experienced with multiple SoC projects for design verification (including STA, DRC, LVS)
- Participated in physical design and tape-out of the world-first Samsung 10nm SoC project

Graduate Research Assistant / Smart Sensor Architecture Laboratory KAIST

02/2011 to 02/2013

Daejeon, South Korea

- Thesis: An Efficient Energy Management for Solar-Powered Wireless Visual Sensor Networks
- Research for an energy management scheme for camera systems with solar-powered batteries in wireless visual sensor networks

Education and Training

Ph.D.: Electrical and Computer Engineering

Expected in 06/2022

La Jolla, CA, USA

UC San Diego

Advised by Prof. Andrew B. Kahng

M.S.: Electrical Engineering

KAIST

02/2013

Advised by Prof. Chong-Min Kyung

Daejeon, South Korea

B.S.: Electrical Engineering

02/2011

Yonsei University

Seoul, South Korea

Publications

(***All papers with Prof. Andrew B. Kahng, have authors listed in alphabetical order)

Journal

- [J2] A. B. Kahng, Minsoo Kim, S. Kim and M. Woo "An Open-Source Rosetta Stone for Physical Design Research", IEEE Design & Test, 2021, in preparation.
- [J1] C.-K. Cheng, A. B. Kahng, H. Kim, Minsoo Kim, D. Lee, D. Park and M. Woo "PROBE2.0: A Systematic Framework for Routability Assessment from Technology to Design in Advanced Nodes", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems, 2021, doi:10.1109/TCAD.2021.3093015.

Conference

- [C10] C.-K. Cheng, A. B. Kahng, I. Kang, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, D. Lee, B. Lin, D. Park and M. Woo, "Core-ECO: Concurrent Refinement of Detailed Place-and-Route for an Efficient ECO Automation", *Proc. IEEE International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD)*, 2021, to appear.
- [C9] C. Chidambaram, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, G. Nallapati, S. C. Song and M. Woo, "A Novel Framework for DTCO: Fast and Automatic Routability Assessment with Machine Learning for Sub-3nm Technology Options", *Proc. IEEE Symposium on VLSI Technology*, 2021, pp. 1-2.
- [C8] H. Fatemi, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and J. Pineda de Gyvez "Optimal Bounded-Skew Steiner Trees to Minimize Maximum k-Active Dynamic Power", Proc. ACM/IEEE International Workshop on System-Level Interconnect Problems and Pathfinding (SLIP), 2020, pp. 1-8.
- [C7] A. Rovinski, T. Ajayi, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, G. Wang and M. Saligane, "Bridging Academic Open-Source EDA to Real-World Usability", *Proc. ACM/IEEE International Conference on Computer-Aided Design (ICCAD)*, 2020, pp. 1-7.
- [C6] V. A. Chhabria, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, U. Mallappa, S. S. Sapatnekar and B. Xu, "Template-based PDN Synthesis in Floorplan and Placement Using Classifier and CNN Techniques", *Proc. ACM/IEEE Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC)*, 2020, pp. 44-49.
- [C5] T. Ajayi, V. A. Chhabria, M. Fogaça, S. Hashemi, A. Hosny, A. B. Kahng, Minsoo Kim, J. Lee, U. Mallappa, M. Neseem, G. Pradipta, S. Reda, M. Saligane, S. S. Sapatnekar, C. Sechen, M. Shalan, W. Swartz, L. Wang, Z. Wang, M. Woo and B. Xu, "Toward an Open-Source Digital Flow: First Learnings from the OpenROAD Project", Proc. ACM/IEEE Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2019, pp. 76:1-76:4.
- [C4] T. Ajayi, D. Blaauw, T.-B. Chan, C.-K. Cheng, V. A. Chhabria, D. K. Choo, M. Coltella, S. Dobre, R. Dreslinski, M. Fogaça, S. Hashemi, A. Hosny, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, J. Li, Z. Liang, U. Mallappa, P. Penzes, G. Pradipta, S. Reda, A. Rovinski, K. Samadi, S. S. Sapatnekar, L. Saul, C. Sechen, V. Srinivas, W. Swartz, D. Sylvester, D. Urquhart, L. Wang, M. Woo and B. Xu, "OpenROAD: Toward a Self- Driving, Open-Source Digital Layout Implementation Tool Chain", *Proc. Government Microcircuit Applications and Critical Technology Conference (GOMACTech)*, 2019, pp. 1105-1110.
- [C3] S. Heo, A. B. Kahng, Minsoo Kim, L. Wang and C. Yang "Detailed Placement for IR Drop Mitigation by Power Staple Insertion in Sub-10nm", Proc. ACM/IEEE Design, Automation and Test in Europe (DATE), 2019, pp. 824-829.
- [C2] S. Heo, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and L. Wang, "Diffusion Break-Aware Leakage Power Optimization and Detailed Placement in Sub-10nm VLSI", Proc. ACM/IEEE Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2019, pp. 550-556. (Nominated for Best Paper award)
- [C1] Minsoo Kim, C.-M. Kyung and K. Yi, "An Energy Management Scheme for Solar-Powered Wireless Visual Sensor Networks Toward Uninterrupted Operations", Proc. IEEE International SoC Design Conference (ISOCC), 2013, pp. 23-26.

Talk

• [T5] C. Chidambaram, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, G. Nallapati, S. C. Song and M. Woo, "A Novel Framework for DTCO: Fast and Automatic Routability Assessment with Machine Learning for Sub-3nm Technology Options", *IEEE Symposium on VLSI Technology*, June 2021.

- [T4] H. Fatemi, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and J. Pineda de Gyvez "Optimal Bounded-Skew Steiner Trees to Minimize Maximum k-Active Dynamic Power", *ACM/IEEE International Workshop on System-Level Interconnect Problems and Pathfinding (SLIP)*, November 2020.
- [T3] Minsoo Kim, "PROBE2.0: A Systematic Framework for Routability Assessment from Technology to Design in Sub-7nm Nodes", C-DEN Workshop, October 2020.
- [T2] S. Heo, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, L. Wang and C. Yang "Detailed Placement for IR Drop Mitigation by Power Staple Insertion in Sub-10nm", *ACM/IEEE Design, Automation and Test in Europe (DATE)*, March 2019.
- [T1] Minsoo Kim, "Mixed-Diffusion Break and Power Stapling Optimizations for Improved PPA in 5nm Technology", C-DEN Workshop, November 2018.

Poster

- [P5] C.-T. Ho, A. B. Kahng, C. Kim, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and L. Wang, "Multi-Bit Combinational Cell Placement for Power Reduction", *C-DEN Workshop*, November 2019.
- [P4] A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and H. Y. Liu, "Gate-Cut-Aware Detailed Placement and Leakage Optimization in Advanced Technologies", *C-DEN Workshop*, June 2019.
- [P3] S. Heo, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u>, L. Wang and C. Yang "Detailed Placement for IR Drop Mitigation by Power Staple Insertion in Sub-10nm VLSI", *C-DEN Workshop*, November 2018.
- [P2] S. Heo, A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and L. Wang "Single vs. Double Diffusion Break: Studies of 2nd DB Impacts on Leakage and Density in Sub-10nm VLSI", *C-DEN Workshop*, May 2018.
- [P1] A. B. Kahng, <u>Minsoo Kim</u> and L. Wang, "Combined Detailed Placement and Power Reduction for 7nm and Beyond IC Technologies", *UCSD Research Expo*, April 2018.